<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joao Moreira - Data Science</title><link href="http://jagmoreira.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jagmoreira.com/feeds/data-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jagmoreira.com/</id><updated>2016-07-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>R v Python: Dawn of Analytics</title><link href="http://jagmoreira.com/r-v-python-dawn-of-analytics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-07-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joao Moreira</name></author><id>tag:jagmoreira.com,2016-07-07:/r-v-python-dawn-of-analytics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A fresh yet slightly biased perspective on the recent data science language war.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've just completed a 3-month internship at a startup that does data consulting for chemical engineering companies. It was a great experience overall and I learned a lot, including how to program in R. You see, the Amaral Lab (where I'm currently doing a PhD) is almost exclusively a Python lab. Every now and then other languages attempt to break in but they never get very far (looking at you Matlab). So, among other reasons, I saw this internship as a good opportunity to learn R since it is one of the main programming languages used in the Data Science world in addition to Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple google search will yield &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=R+vs+python"&gt;tons of R vs. Python comparisons&lt;/a&gt; and people can be very entrenched in either camp. Regardless, not having read such a comparison (true!) before starting my internship I thought I would try to share my fresh yet slightly biased perspective on this data science language war by focusing on a few key points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a general-purpose programming language created by Guido van Rossum in 1991. It's a high-level programming language built with a focus on readability and simplicity of syntax. Despite this (or because of this) it is an extremely popular language used in many applications, with an extensive &lt;a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;library&lt;/a&gt; of third-party packages. R is a programming language created by Ross Ihaka and Robert Gentleman in 1993. Unlike Python, R was developed mainly for use in statistical analysis. Because of its specificity, R is faster than Python in some computations. Just like Python, R also has a very large &lt;a href="https://cloud.r-project.org"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; of packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of syntax, both languages have dynamic typing (no need to specify the type of a variable before assigning a value to it), support loops and conditionals, and use logic and math symbols in mostly the same ways. Python is famous for its use of indentation to delimit blocks of code while R is more "classic" in that it requires curly braces for any block of code longer than a single line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In R, variable types (number, string, logical, etc.) can be either a single value or a vector of values, whereas Python has both simple variable types (int, float, string, bool) and collection types (list, tuple, etc.). R also allows lists of variables which are not necessarily vectors! Sometimes, in order to achieve the desired behavior you need to unlist a variable first. I found this very baffling at first. Yet, because of R's built-in vector capabilities there's very little need for explicit for-loops. Consequently, a vector operation in R is usually faster than the equivalent for-loop-based operation. Similar performance in Python would require the array datatype provided by the numpy package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main structure used to analyse data is arguably the dataframe. It's essentially a table of data with convenient properties that allow for manipulation of whole columns/rows of data. It exists natively in R but often the &lt;a href="https://cran.rstudio.com/web/packages/dplyr/vignettes/introduction.html"&gt;dplyr&lt;/a&gt; package is used to expand the dataframe manipulation tools. Python also has dataframes via the &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org"&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt; package. In my experience, both languages provide very similar dataframe functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very big and important difference between R and Python is how they organize documentation. In R, documentation for several related functions are grouped together. First there's a list of all related functions, then a table with the combined arguments of all the functions, followed by a wall of text explaining what each function does and what the return values are. For an example, see the page for &lt;a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/base/html/grep.html"&gt;grep&lt;/a&gt;. In Python, every function is instead documented separately. The arguments and return value are always listed but not always fully explained. The closest Python equivalent to R's grep is the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/re.html"&gt;re module&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, most data scientists seek to share their work online. This entails creating a web-app to showcase data and/or visualization while hosting it in a server somewhere. Python users typically turn to &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://flask.pocoo.org"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; for the app creation. This process can be quite cumbersome as, much like Python itself, these frameworks are general purpose: Flask is just a bare-bones package for web apps while the more powerful Django has a &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.9/intro/"&gt;7-part tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on how to make a simple poll!
The process is much easier with R. Using &lt;a href="http://shiny.rstudio.com"&gt;Shiny&lt;/a&gt;, a R-based web framework, you can have an interactive web app with plots up and running locally in just a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're starting to learn how to program in Python you may be using the excellent &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org"&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt;. This browser-based programming tool is great for quick coding and data visualization. The &lt;a href="https://irkernel.github.io"&gt;R kernel&lt;/a&gt; for Jupyter is relatively new so there are still some kinks, but the tool is in active development so expect improvements soon. Still, R in Jupyter already allows for much of the same testing/visualization available via the python kernel. A solid, and much more powerful, alternative for R programming is &lt;a href="https://www.rstudio.com"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; (Shiny was built by the RStudio people). It's a fully featured IDE that is very easy to set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, where do I stand on this great war? ... Well, nowhere really. As is often the case, the truth lies somewhere in the middle. As I outlined above, Python and R have different strengths and are by no means mutually exclusive. Why choose a single language for all things when you can mix the best of both worlds?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="R"></category></entry><entry><title>Dataclysm: The very best of</title><link href="http://jagmoreira.com/dataclysm-the-very-best-of.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-25T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-02-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Joao Moreira</name></author><id>tag:jagmoreira.com,2015-02-25:/dataclysm-the-very-best-of.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read Dataclysm by Christian Rudder. These are some of my favorite stories from this book.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="http://dataclysm.org"&gt;Dataclysm&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/christianrudder"&gt;Christian Rudder&lt;/a&gt;. If you don't know him, Christian Rudder is one of the founders of &lt;a href="https://www.okcupid.com"&gt;OkCupid&lt;/a&gt;, a very popular online dating website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In OKCupid, as in other dating websites, users create a profile, put up some pictures, and write some stuff about themselves. They can then rate other users and send them private messages with the purpose of getting a date and, if they are lucky, find that special someone. When you're creating your profile and from time to time, the website also asks you several questions, some of their answers will be kept private, others will be put up on their profile pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OKCupid website has a companion blog, &lt;a href="http://blog.okcupid.com"&gt;OkTrends&lt;/a&gt;, where its creators (the DataCupids!) discuss and analyze trends and stereotypes, debunk myths, give advice, and much more, all using data from OKCupid. Dataclysm takes some of the most popular stories from this blog, expands them, and adds in a few more external datasets (Twitter, Facebook, Reddit, just to name a few) for extra punch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dataclysm is essentially about making sense of Big Data. It's about how, faced with a deluge (cataclysm) of data, we can use good data analysis to draw great insights. More generally the book presents an uplifting message that many insights that would otherwise have required years of work, expensive setups, and many test subjects, are now possible with careful analysis of existing datasets. Instead of doing an intensive review of the book, which is but a simple google search away, I will instead highlight some of my favorite stories from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Men of all ages prefer 20 year old women.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may seem shocking at first it actually make some sense from a biological perspective. Males are hardwired to "spread their seed" so it makes sense that they would look for the most fertile females. In contrast, women exhibit much more socially acceptable preferences: women under 30 prefer men slightly older than themselves; women over 30 prefer men slightly younger than themselves, although never going above 40. Does this mean the human race is doomed? Are all men perverts? Probably not. When looking at the actual messaging rates for men, the datacupids found that men actually message women who are at most 9 years younger than them. This is possibly due to social stigma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Is Twitter degrading our language?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may know, Twitter messages are limited to 140 characters. Because of this apparent restriction it did not take long before people started predicting that language skills would begin to degrade with increasing Twitter use. That, in fact, did not happen. The datacupids compared the most common words on Twitter with those from the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Most_common_words_in_English"&gt;Oxford English Corpus&lt;/a&gt; (OEC) (the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; repository of modern english words) and found that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The average Twitter word is 4.3 characters long compared to 3.4 in the OEC;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter's top 100 word list which do not show up in the OEC are heavily related to feelings and declarative nouns such as home, life, best, today, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in fact, Twitter's limit of 140 characters is not a restriction but a catalyst for innovation.  "Twitterites" increase the information density of their communications. They jump straight to the point, be it breakfast or landing on comets.
&lt;strong&gt;Myth busted!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Love is blind.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, to conclusively prove that love is blind, OKCupid removed all profiles photos from the website for a few hours. Well, not really. It was actually to promote a mobile app called &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crazy_Blind_Date"&gt;Crazy Blind Date&lt;/a&gt;. During that day, the number of messages exchanged on the website abruptly dropped to almost zero! While the app itself lasted only a few months, it still managed to serve blind dates to about 10,000 people. How did they feel about those blind dates? &lt;a href="http://blog.okcupid.com/index.php/we-experiment-on-human-beings/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;They loved them&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/a&gt; Users, both male and female, reported having a great time, regardless of the other person's attractiveness. Maybe there is some truth to this myth after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;There are no borders anymore.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one isn't really a story but a whole chapter providing evidence to something that is becoming more and more evident and that yet many world leaders still refuse to accept for whatever reason: Physical borders not cultural borders. The internet has totally redefined how we can chart cultural similarity. A few years ago &lt;a href="http://petewarden.com/about/"&gt;Pete Warden&lt;/a&gt; scrapped Facebook data and calculated the clusters from the USA user connections. He &lt;a href="http://petewarden.com/2010/02/06/how-to-split-up-the-us/"&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that people belonged to one of 7 "states" instead of the physical 50. In a maybe-not-so-different context, the datacupids found a totally different set of borders. Reddit, the front page of the internet, is organized into thousand of themed "subreddits". Looking at the most popular ones, and the frequency of posts across the different subreddits, the datacupids &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2014/10/mapmaking_using_reddit_okcupid_twitter_and_other_social_media_websites.html"&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; a thriving "country" whose "state" borders are defined by common interests and location defined by similarity of interests.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data science"></category><category term="review"></category></entry></feed>